<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Pretended Yearly Meeting of the Quakers, their nameless bull of excommunication given forth against George Keith from a party or faction of men that call themselves the Yearly Meeting, which they would have to be received as the general judgment and sentence of the Quakers ; with a brief answer to the same, shewing that for his zealous and consciencious opposing their gross errors, and reproving the evil and wicked practices of them in Pennsylvania, whom they own to be their breathern, particularly their persecution of G. Keith, and some of his friends, that party has excommunicated him.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K193</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1084</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13659574</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13659574</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101063</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47165)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101063)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 792:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Pretended Yearly Meeting of the Quakers, their nameless bull of excommunication given forth against George Keith from a party or faction of men that call themselves the Yearly Meeting, which they would have to be received as the general judgment and sentence of the Quakers ; with a brief answer to the same, shewing that for his zealous and consciencious opposing their gross errors, and reproving the evil and wicked practices of them in Pennsylvania, whom they own to be their breathern, particularly their persecution of G. Keith, and some of his friends, that party has excommunicated him.</title>
                  <author>Society of Friends. London Yearly Meeting.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Levis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pennsylvania.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101063:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Pretended Yearly Meeting OF THE QUAKERS, THEIR <hi>Nameleſs Bull</hi> OF EXCOMMUNICATION Given forth againſt George Keith, From a Party or Faction of Men that call themſelves the <hi>Yearly Meeting,</hi> which they would have to be received, as the general Judgment, and Sentence of the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a brief Anſwer to the ſame, ſhewing that for his Zealous and Conſciencious oppoſing their groſs Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and reproving the evil and wicked Practiſes of them in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> whom they own to be their Brethren, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly their Perſecution of <hi>G. Keith,</hi> and ſome of his Friends, that party has Excommunicated him.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>R. Levis,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="bull_of_excommunication">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101063:2"/>
            <head>At the Yearly Meeting in <hi>London,</hi> the 17. of the 3d. Month. 1695.</head>
            <p>THis Meeting taking notice of the Iudgment and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the laſt Yearly Meeting, concerning <hi>George Keith,</hi> and inquiring whether he had Anſwered the Senſe and Advice, which in the Name of the Lord, that Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then delivered to him, doth find that he hath not only not followed the Chriſtian Advice and Iudgment of that Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but hath Rejected it, and Printed againſt it, denying it to be the Iudgment or Senſe of the Yearly Meeting, and affirming that Meeting that gave it forth, not to be the Year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meeting, but a party or Faction.</p>
            <p>And alſo, That he hath, ſince the laſt Yearly Meeting, been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry troubleſome and burthenſome to Friends in publick-Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in and about this City, as was Teſtified in his preſence by many faithful Friends, who were Eye and Ear Witneſſes thereof. And in this Meeting the ſaid <hi>Geo. Keith,</hi> did openly Read a Paper of his, containing Reflections, Accuſations and Exceptions againſt divers Friends, that are members of this Meeting, in which Paper he Iuſtifleth himſelf in thoſe things, for which the laſt Yearly Meeting Reproved and Cenſured him, and in what he hath Printed ſince. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afterwards deſired to come into the Meeting again, and acquainted with the great diſſatisfaction which the Meeting had concerning him, with reſpect to what he had printed, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and done againſt Truth and Friends; he brake forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to great diſorder, and very unſeemly behaviour, uttering many bitter and unſavory Expreſſions, and in a very angry manner roſe up, and departed before the further Senſe and Iudgment of the Meeting could be given him.</p>
            <p>All which this Meeting taking into their weighty Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and being fully ſatisfied, both by his Printed Books and other outward Evidences, with reſpect to matters of Fact, and by that Divine Senſe, which in the openings of the Heavenly Life, ran as a mighty ſtream through the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and was confirmed and ſealed by many living Teſtime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, born in the Name of the Lord, and in the powerful demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101063:2"/>of the Holy Spirit; That the ſaid <hi>Geo. Keith,</hi> of late hath been, and yet is acted by an unchriſtian Spirit, which hath moved and led him to ſtir up contention and ſtrife in the Church of Chriſt, and to cauſe Diviſions, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations and Breaches amongſt them that profeſs the Truth and that the tendency of divers of his late writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and actings hath been to Expoſe the Truth, and the Friends thereof to the Reproach of the World, did unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly agree, and declare it to be the Senſe and Iudgment of this meeting; And it is the ſenſe and judgment of this Meeting, That the ſaid <hi>George Keith</hi> is gone from the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Vnity of the peaceable Spirit of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and hath thereby ſeperated himſeif from the Holy Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Church of Chriſt, and that whilſt he is in an unreconciled and uncharitable ſtate, he ought not to preach or pray in any Friends Meetings, nor he Owned or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as one of Vs, until by a publick and hearty Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the great Offence he hath given, and hurt he hath done, and Condemnation of himſelf therefore, he <hi>give Proof of his unfeigned Repentance,</hi> and do his endeavour to remove and take off the Reproach he hath brought upon Truth and Friends, which in the <hi>love of God,</hi> we heartily deſire for his Souls ſake.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed by appointment of the Yearly Meeting, and in behalf thereof as their Act, which is to my own certain knowledge. <hi>Benjamin Bealing.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer_to_bull_of_excommunication">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101063:3"/>
            <head>A brief Anſwer to the foregoing Nameleſs B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL of Excommunication</head>
            <p>A Paper bearing this Title, <hi>At the Yearly Meeting in</hi> London, <hi>the 17th of the 3d Month,</hi> 1695. And having at the end of it theſe following words, <hi>Signed by the appointment of the Yearly Meeting, and in behalf thereof, as their Act, which is to my certain knowledg,</hi> Benjamin Bealing, came to my Houſe, and was delivered to ſome in my Family, the 17th of this Inſtant 1695; the which Paper mentioneth no ſort of People, nor what ſort of yearly meeting it came from; and tho it is ſigned by one <hi>Benj. Bealing,</hi> who ſaith he ſigned it by the apoointment of the Yearly Meeting (yet he telleth not what <hi>Yearly Meeting</hi>) did ſo appoint him; and whereas he ſaith to his own certain Knowledge, is that enough? How doth he make it appear to others, that it is to his own certain knowledg? Is it either Chriſtian or Human, or agreeable to any civil Conſtitution, or Religious Society, to give forth a defamatory Paper in the Name of a People, and not tell who or what that People is? And tho I do not in the leaſt pretend ignorance, ſo as not to know ſome particular perſons who have had a main hand in it, and whoſe work principally it is; yet it appeareth not whom they mean by what they call the Yearly Meeting; if granted it comes from that called the Yearly Meeting of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> as whether they mean only ſuch a ſelect number conſiſting of two perſons, ſent up to <hi>London,</hi> from every County in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> or from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Quarterly Meeting in the ſeveral Counties, together with them they call <hi>Publick Friends,</hi> or <hi>Friends of the Ministry,</hi> who aſſume a Power to make Laws, and give forth Edicts or Decrees to bind and oblige the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of all theſe many thouſands in the three Nations, and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the World, that go under the outward profeſſion and denomination of <hi>Quakers,</hi> and profeſs to be one Body of People with them. And that this ſelect number of Miniſters, and choſen members from the ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who in great part are Miniſters, and Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ners paid by the reſpective Counties for that Service, and oft deſignedly choſen to bring to effect
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101063:3"/>ſomething contrived beforehand by a particular Cabal of ſome particular perſons, excluding generally others of the ſame Profeſſion, whom they own to be in Unity with them, from being members in the ſaid Yearly Meeting, or from being priviledged to meddle in Church Affairs with them. If this is meant by the Yearly Meeting, that hath ſent this Paper to me; I diſown all ſuch conſtitution of a Yearly Meeting, as not only not being warranted by Scripture, but contradictory thereunto; and alſo to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and approved Doctrine in <hi>R. B.</hi> his Book, called the <hi>Anarchy, &amp;c.</hi> highly approved by the Principal Teachers and Leaders among the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and hath been twice Printed by them, and great uſe hath been made of it, eſpecially againſt ſuch as have differed from them about ſome particular caſes, and circumſtances of Church Diſcipline and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. For thus he ſaith, p. 78, 79. (giving ſome of the differences betwixt the <hi>Romanists,</hi> and the generality of theſe called Proteſtants on the one hand, and the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> on the other hand) <hi>That whereas thoſe in matters of difference, only allow theſe of the Clergy, ſo call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> i. e. <hi>the Miniſtery, to give a Iudgment with other ſelect perſons choſen, the People called</hi> Quakers <hi>exclude no Member of the Church to give his Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> See further to the ſame purpoſe, p. 81.85. And I further ſay, For any number of men to aſſume a Power, in an aſſembly, to extend to all others, as ſuppoſe many thouſands, that what judgment, or ſentence they ſhall paſs, relating either to things of Religion, or Perſons, ſhall oblige the Conſciences of all theſe thouſands under the ſame profeſſion, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Unity with them, is directly contrary to that Chriſtian Liberty wherewith Chriſt has made every true Chriſtian free, and is a Popiſh and Tyrannical Invaſion, and Uſurpation over Mens Conſciences, which as I have formerly born my Teſtimony againſt, ſo I ſtill do. And it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent enough, that ſuch who have given out this Paper againſt we, was not any free Meeting, where any that have a mind (owned by them to be in Unity) might not be preſent, and freely give their Judgment, without any Threatning or Terrification, becauſe, to my certain Knowledg, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, I ſaw the Door of the Meeting, where that called the Year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meeting Sate, kept by three or four perſons, that refuſed to let in, ſome that deſired to come in, and yet were owned by them, and it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently known, they who keep the Door let in or keep out ſuch as they think fit: But again, ſuch whom they let in, if they be not of the Miniſtry, nor any of the two choſen out of every County, they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed only to be there as ſtanders by, and Spectators, but have no allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to give any Judgment in the Caſe, which hath been a diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſome Honeſt Friends, owned by the Yearly Meeting as Friends, from coming to the Meeting, being only permitted to be there as Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</p>
            <p>And yet further, It is ſufficiently known, the way that they take, either by perſwaſions or terrifications to gain the univerſal and unanimous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of them, called, <hi>The Commiſſioners, or choſen Members from every
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101063:4"/>County;</hi> as doth plainly appear by the late moſt abſurd and inſolent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, more like the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> than a free Aſſembly of ſincere Chriſtians, they did take with a Preacher, one of their Commiſioners, or choſen Members, who having ſaid in private, out of the Meeting, he could ſooner Die, or looſe his Right-Hand, than ſign to a Paper diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>George Keith,</hi> which coming to their Intelligence, that there was ſuch a Perſon, but not knowing who he was, they were ſo earneſt to find him out, that they cauſed call over the Roll, or liſt of the Names of the Perſons ſent from the reſpective Counties, to find out this perſon, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them one by one, to find him out, and the poor man, not daring to lye, owned he was the Perſon, and being terrified, leſt he ſhould be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely proceeded againſt by them; he came (with ſome others to be Witneſſes to his Recantation) and diſowned to me what he had formerly ſaid, tho a few hours before, he profeſſed ſo great a concern and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Conſcience towards me. This paſſage is ſo conſiderable an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance towards the erecting the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition</hi> among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> that I hope ſome will be awakened to take notice of it, and withſtand it.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Whatever they may boaſt of their Act againſt me, as being the unanimous Act of the Yearly Meeting; yet ſeeing many preſent, owned to be Friends in Unity with them, gave no ſignification of their owning that ſentence; and I am loth to be ſo uncharitable as to think they did own it, not being ſo much as enquired, whether they did or not, being conſidered as Members; and that divers, ſome whereof I have a certain knowledg, did voluntarily and purpoſely abſent from the Meeting, leſt any ſuch thing ſhould be required of them, as to own ſuch an unrighteous Act, tho it had been more Noble, and more like a free Chriſtian Spirit purpoſely to have come (if they had found entrance) and Witneſſed againſt it: But what the deſign of this Omiſſion is for them, to ſend forth a nameleſs Paper againſt me, which is to go over all places of the World, where the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> have their Meetings, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring it to be their ſenſe, That I ought not to Preach and Pray in any of Friends Meetings, nor be owned and received as one of them; ye ſee it is of an univerſal extent, without all Limitation of places, which is to make their Yearly Meeting at <hi>London,</hi> conſiſting of a few particulars, as Univerſal as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> maketh her ſelf to be; I ſay, it is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of enquiry what the deſign is, that ſuch an Edict or Sentence ſhould go forth againſt me, from an Aſſembly or Meeting, who give themſelves no particular deſignation, Name, or Denomination of diſtinction from other People, Is it not this plain Evidence in matter of Fact, that this their Judgment or Sentence againſt me is a work of Darkneſs, acted and brought forth in the Dark, notwithſtanding all their high pretences to the light, and to act and do all in the light? Is it not a Birth without a legitimate Father, a Nameleſs Child, having no proper Name to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh it, as Baſtards frequently and Fondlings, have no proper Names whereby to know their true Fathers?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101063:4"/>
            <p>As for the Contents of the ſaid Bull, as it is nameleſs, ſo it may be ſaid to have neither Horns, nor Teeth, nor any thing of juſt matter or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which they in particular charge againſt me, conſiſting almoſt wholly in bare generals, which prove nothing. They alledg they are ſatisfied, both by my printed Books, and other outward Evidences, with reſpect to matters of Fact, and by that Divine ſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That the ſaid <hi>George Keith</hi> hath been of late, and yet is acted by an unchriſtian Spirit. But this is only ſaid, but no paſſages in any of my Books brought againſt me, to ſatisfy any moderate inquirer, nor any outward Evidence, with reſpect to matter of Fact, ſo much as alledged to prove their general Charge; and as for the pretence to a Divine ſenſe, it is but vain and preſumptuous, ſo to judg a Man to be of an unchriſtian Spirit, without external Evidence in matter of Doctrine and Fact brought againſt me, none of which they have brought. And ſeeing by that which they call a Divine Senſe, they have falſely and unjuſtly judged me, without giving any proof of their charge. I am bold and free in my Spirit to ſay their Senſe is not Divine, but Carnal, and Senſual, for no Divine Senſe will lead any man, or men to be falſe Accuſers. But whereas they ſay, the Divine Senſe in the openings of the Heavenly Life, ran, as a mighty ſtream, through the Meeting, they writ nonſenſically, confounding the Life, with the ſence that the Life gives, for it is moſt improper to ſay, That mens ſenſe runs through a Meeting, tho the Life that gives it doth in the Aſſembly of the Faithful, as it ſealeth to a Righteous Judgment; but this their Judgment being unrighteous, it hath neither the Divine Life nor Senſe to feal it, but that a Power of Darkneſs might run through the Meeting, and deceive many by its falſe appearance of Life, is probable.</p>
            <p>In my Paper I delivered to them at their Meeting, I demanded them to let me know what they had againſt me, either in Doctrine, or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Life and Converſation, and was moſt willing to have been brought to a Trial before them, making my juſt exceptions againſt ſome perſons, from being either Evidences againſt me, or Judges in the Caſe, becauſe of their known Prejudice; but without all due Tryal. they have given out this Nameleſs Bull againſt me, having nothing of any real ſubſtance or matter of juſt occaſion againſt me; and therefore it is but waſte, either of Time or Paper, to give them any other but a general Anſwer to their bare general Charge, having ſufficiently, by way of Anticipation, to this their raſh and imprudent Act, as well as injurious, cleared my ſelf of all theſe general Charges they caſt upon me, in my Paper I delivered to them at their Yearly meeting, and in the brief Narrative of the chief and moſt material Paſſages of diſcourſe that paſſed betwixt ſome of them and me in the ſaid <hi>Meeting</hi> at two ſeveral times, both lately Printed together, wherein I anſwer at length to their general and indefinit Accuſation, That I have not followed the Chriſtian Advice and Judgment of the laſt Yearly <hi>Meeting;</hi> but if they had not been Conſcious to themſelves, that that part of it I did not follow, and for which they have given out this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101063:5"/>raſh, and injurious Sentence againſt me, was unchriſtian; why did they not particularly, and diſtinctly mention that Adviſe, <q>Which was to clear the Body of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and their <hi>Miniſters</hi> from the groſs Errors charged on ſome in <hi>America,</hi>
               </q> which I have with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience refuſed to do, becauſe to my certain knowledg, and which I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered at their Meeting, to prove ſome of their chief Teachers, preſent in the ſaid Meeting, are guilty of divers of the ſame groſs Errors charged on ſome in <hi>America,</hi> and which I have in part ſufficiently demonſtrated in Print, in that called a Liſt.</p>
            <p>And as I have occaſion, may further demonſtrate out of their own Printed Books. But let none think ſtrange that I have not made this diſcovery of their groſs Errors till now, at leaſt ſo to expoſe them in Print, for I ſincerely declare that the worſt and groſſeſt ſort of their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, whom I now expoſe to publick view; I did not know they were guilty of them, or that they were to be found in their Books but of late times, and after I had diſcovered them, to my own certain knowledg, I was willing to exerciſe Chriſtian Patience; if by any means, they might have been perſwaded, to have Corrected them, having privately warned and admoniſhed ſome of them, and having alſo at divers times in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way of Teſtimony in their hearing, declared againſt theſe Errors. But inſtead of their hearkening to my Teſtimony, and amending theſe Errors, they became my Enemy for telling them the Truth; and now they having cut off all hope or expectation, that they will receive any brotherly Advice from me, by this their moſt Hoſtile way of appearing againſt me, I am conſtrain'd thus to appear, not in any Enmity againſt them, but in Love to the Truth, and the Honour of it, which I ought to Love and Honour above all men, and alſo in Love to the Souls of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ignorant perſons, whom they have Blinded and Darkned, and led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe groſs Errors, to the great danger of the Salvation of their Souls, that they might be undeceived. And whereas they make it a matter of Accuſation againſt me, that I denied that Paper, called <hi>A true Account,</hi> which they call <hi>The Chriſtian Advice and Judgment of the Yearly Meeting,</hi> to be the Judgment or Senſe of the Yearly Meeting, affirming that <hi>Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> that gave it forth, not to be the <hi>Yearly Meeting,</hi> but a Party or Fact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, which is the only true particular thing that I obſerve in all their <hi>Nameleſs Bull,</hi> that they bring againſt me. Is this ſo hainous a matter, to deſerve Excommunication, and totally to be Rejected and diſowned, not only as a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> but as one of that People. We ſee to what a great height they are come to, in a ſhort time, <hi>Rome</hi> did not ariſe to that height in full ten times the length of time, that this which calleth it ſelf the <hi>Yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meeting,</hi> and Church of Chriſt, hath raiſed it ſelf unto, within the ſpace of a few years; So that if a man will but ſpeak a word concerning the <hi>Yearly Meeting</hi> of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> That it is not a free <hi>Meeting</hi> not duly conſtituted, tho he can ever ſo Evidently proven, as I have done ſufficiently, no leſs cenſure ſhall paſs on him than an Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101063:5"/>and off-cutting. But thanks be to God, whatever humane Authority they uſurp, to cut me off from ſome particular viſible Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or Perſons, they have no Divine authority or Power, to cut me off either from Chriſt, or his faithful Followers, and their Bull is but an empty blaſt of Air, that hath not killed, nor I hope ever ſhall kill the Life of my Soul, or that Holy Fellowſhip, I have had, and ſtill have with a faithful and ſincere Remnant among that People; and for all their emnity hatred, reproaches, revilings, curſes, woes and plagues that they have poured out againſt me, in publick Meetings, both in Preaching and Prayer, acted to be ſure by an unchriſtian Spirit, I return them Love and Goodwil, bleſſing for curſing, good for evil, earneſtly Praying that God may give them Repentance, and Forgiveneſs, for this their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian way of Proceeding againſt me, and for all their other Errors, and that they may be recovered both out of the many groſs Errors, they are held in, by the power of Darkneſs, notwithſtanding their high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to Light; and alſo out of their height of Pride, and ſelf Exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which God in his great mercy grant, if it be his bleſſed will; and it is my great comfort, that notwithſtanding their great Provocations, I never felt a Curſe, or any thing like it, either in my mouth, or heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any. And they may be greatly aſhamed to accuſe me, in this their nameleſs Bull, as they do; if they were not greatly hardened, that I have been very troubleſome, and burthenſome to Friends in publick, meetings, ſince the laſt Yearly Meeting, which being but a bare general without mentioning any particular words or deeds, or geſture, wherein I was ſuch, I might reject as little worth noticing.</p>
            <p>But I cannot well let paſs their exceeding great Partiality, in taking no notice of the great Abuſes, and moſt unchriſtian uſages I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from time to time, from ſome of their chief Preachers by moſt uncivil Interruptions, contrary not only to the Goſpel-order, but to the Law of the Nation, whereas none can truly ſay, that ever I inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted any of them; alſo by their moving themſelves to Preach and Pray, and moving one another, and ſo cloſely ſpeaking one after another on purpoſe to Exclude my Teſtimony; and their moſt bitter Reflections, Revilings, Reproaches, falſe Accuſations, falſe Prophecies and Curſes that divers of them have poured out againſt me, as particularly <hi>Charles Marſhal, W. Penn, W. Bingley,</hi> and <hi>J. Vaughton,</hi> both in Preaching and Prayer; and tho <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> hath carried it a little more ſmoothly, than thoſe others, yet his prejudice hath ſufficiently vented it ſelf alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me in publick Meetings; yea, even in Prayer, and ſuch profanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Prayer in the pretended Exerciſe of their Extemporal Gift, aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a moſt ſinful liberty to vend their ſinful paſſions, and animoſities againſt them, at whom they are prejudiced, as it is abomination in the ſight of God, ſo it is moſt loathſome and offenſive to Men of tender Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and giveth to many occaſion to ſay, a ſet Form of Prayer, is leſs of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, and more Edifying than ſuch paſſionate Rapſodies, that too many
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101063:6"/>uſe, and yet do call them Praying by the Holy Spirit. But whatever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences theſe men have againſt me, who have publiſhed this Nameleſs Bull, in accuſing me of being Contentious, cauſing Diviſions Seperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Breaches among Friends, and other bare general, but falſe Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which require no particular Anſwer, the bottom and foundation of all this, and of my being thought ſo burdenſom and troubleſome to them in Meetings, is becauſe they cannot endure ſound Doctrine, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially their deep prejudice againſt my frequent Preaching the great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Faith in Chriſt Crucified, as neceſſary to Regeneration, Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and eternal Salvation, and alſo the Reſurrection of the Dead, and Chriſt's coming without us, in his Glorified Body, to Judg the Quick and the Dead; all which have ſeemed as new and ſtrange Doctrin to them, and ſome have more directly, and ſome more indirectly oppoſed it, and about the time of the laſt Yearly Meeting, <hi>William Edminſon</hi> at the <hi>Bull and Mouth,</hi> in the hearing of hundreds, as well as in my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, boldly affirmed, <hi>It was not needful to Preach Chriſt's Death and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings in Friends Meetings. William Penn</hi> lately affirmed at <hi>Ratcliffe-Meeting,</hi> (where he falſely accuſed me to be an Apoſtate,) <hi>That Friends ſee not cauſe to Preach that Doctrine much, becauſe all</hi> England <hi>and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, have an Hiſtorical Belief of Chriſt's Death, and Sufferings, and it doth not profit them; and as it was the Diſpenſation of the Apoſtles to Preach Chriſt outwardly, it is our diſpenſation to Preach him inwardly. W. Bingly</hi> hath Preached, <hi>That People that come to Meetings generally believe well enough in Chriſt without, but they want to have Chriſt Preached within, that they may believe in him within;</hi> thus making two Faiths. And to the ſame purpoſe hath <hi>Charles Marſhall</hi> frequently Preached; and alſo ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times he hath ſaid in Publick Meetings, <hi>It is not needful for a Man to ſtand up, and Preach Chriſt's Death and Sufferings from Morning to Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeeing it was generally Believed,</hi> And alſo ſeveral times he Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in publick Meetings, as at <hi>Grace-Church-ſtreet,</hi> and at <hi>Devonſhire-houſe, That the Conſcience muſt firſt be purified, before Faith can be received.</hi> Which falſe Doctrine I did ſeveral times contradict in publick, by ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by true Faith the Conſcience is Purged, and they go along toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and by the Lively Exerciſe of Faith, the Conſcience is gradually Purged, and not all at once, And <hi>John Gratton</hi> ſaid about the time of the laſt Yearly Meeting, in the Publick Meeting in <hi>Grace-Church-Street, To believe that Chriſt died, was the Drunkards Faith, and the Whoremongers Faith;</hi> adding further, <hi>That none had Benefit by Chriſt's Death, but ſuch as are Dead with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus generally they Declare their great ignorance of the true. Faith of Chriſt's Death and ſufferings, Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion, and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, making it only an Hiſtorical and Literal Faith; whereas as there is an Hiſtorical and Literal Faith only of it, that Drunkards and ill Livers may have, as they may have of Chriſt within Notionally and Hiſtorically, ſo there is a living effectual Faith of Chriſt's Death and Sufferings,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101063:6"/>wrought by the Living Power of God in the Hearts of ſincere believers, which Power doth in Gods ordinary way accompany the ſincere Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel, even outwardly, and other outward helps, and means of Juſtification, and all men have a Benefit by Chriſt's Death and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to wit, a day of Viſitation, and any Light and Grace that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly given to men, and the way and manner to come to witneſs a Dying and Riſing with Chriſt, is to believe by the Operation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, that Chriſt Died for Mens Sins, and Roſe again, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that great Love of God, that he ſpared not his Son, but freely gave him for us, and alſo to believe the great Love of Chriſt, who freely gave himſelf for us, by which Faith men come to Witneſs a being Dead with Chriſt, and alſo a being Raiſed with him; and ſeeing this true Faith is wrought in God's ordinary way by Preaching, therefore the true Faith of Chriſt's Death and Sufferings ought to be one of the firſt and chiefeſt things that every true Miniſter ought to Preach, and build up his hearers in, in order to bring them to Communion with God, and Chriſt in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and that they may witneſs God and Chriſt, to dwell in them, and rule in them.</p>
            <p>Another great cauſe of their paſſing this unjuſt Sentence againſt me, is, That I refuſed to call in the Book Printed ſince the laſt Yearly Meeting, called, <hi>The Cauſeleſs Ground,</hi> wherein I expoſtulate the caſe, not only with reſpect to their too great connivance of the vile and groſs Errors, whereof I proved ſome guilty in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> owned by them to be their Brethren, but alſo, with reſpect to their Connivance at, and covering the evil practiſes of their Perſecuting Brethren there, and their moſt illegal and arbitrary Proceedings againſt me, contrary to the Fundamental Laws of all Nations, to the danger of my Life, as well as of my Reputation; for the more particular account whereof, I refer the Reader, to the above cited Book, called, <hi>The Cauſeleſs Ground,</hi> and my Printed Anſwer to their Proclamation, and alſo to the Printed Tryal, relating to <hi>Th. Budd</hi> and me, in the Book called, <hi>New-England's Spirit of Perſecution,</hi> &amp;c. And all this they have paſſed over, both in their former Yearly Meeting, 1694. and alſo in this laſt, 1695, without the leaſt cenſure, a ſufficient Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their partiality, and that a prevailing Faction, or Party of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Men, ruleth in that called the Yearly Meeting, and that therefore what Edict, or Judgment goeth forth from that pretended Yearly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ought not to be called the Act, or Judgment of the Body of that People, it being ſufficiently known that many, even owned by them, as their Brethren here in <hi>England,</hi> and elſewhere, have greatly been diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the Perſecution raiſed againſt us by them in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and have declared againſt it, as well as their other Proceedings. And had all there preſent at the Yearly Meeting, ſo called, been unanimous in their unjuſt Sentence againſt me, and ten times more a greater Number with them; yea, ſuppoſe they can get this their unjuſt Sentence againſt me, confirmed by all their Quarterly and Monthly Meetings in <hi>England,</hi> which yet I think
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101063:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>it will be a very hard, if not impoſſible thing for them to obtain, yet this doth not prove that they are not a Faction or Party, ſeeing it is ſufficiently known, that for many Years paſt, there hath been a Breach amongſt the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> in relation to the Church Government of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and other Circumſtantial Things, impoſed by a Party among them.</p>
            <p>Now of them, of the other ſide, that oppoſe ſome humane Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, called by ſome of the Impoſers, but civil things, as many do well own, and approve me in my publick Teſtimony againſt the vile Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, held by ſome of the contrary part; ſo I know not any that diſown me, or that approve of this Sentence, that this Party that call themſelves indefinitely, the Yearly Meeting, have given againſt me, and yet there is a conſiderable number and body of them.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Whereas they ſeem to blame me, for my departing out of their Yearly Meeting, before the further ſenſe and Judgment of the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing could be given me, which they ſay I did in a very angry manner. But they ſhould have ſaid divers of them, particularly <hi>George VVhitehead</hi> and <hi>VVill. Penn</hi> did in a moſt angry manner, moſt unjuſtly and falſly accuſe me, and behave themſelves moſt unchriſtianly towards me, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the Printed Narrative I have made publick, and I know no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due or unſavory Expreſſion (which they only Charge me with in general) I uttered among them, the greateſt paſſion I was in, was that of Grief, to ſee their moſt unjuſt and inhuman proceedings; and I remember not in the leaſt, that the Meeting, or any in the Meeting deſired me to ſtay, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I roſe up to go, and therefore I ſee not, why I ſhould be blamed for going, having no occaſion to ſtay longer with them, nor any expectation, they would hear my juſt Complaint, or give me any Tryal, but as it hath come to paſs as I expected, they would, have condemned me without any Tryal, fair or unfair.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The 28th day of the 3d. Month, 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>G. Keith.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
